John and Ginny Dildine collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Sound Recordings
  - AFC 1975/001: SR020, Recorded: 1958-10-08, RXG 0711; 26:37
    This seems to be a recording for two short radio programs with Paul Clayton and Char (Charlotte) Daniels. An unidentified guitar instrumental it may be "Bully of the Town" is played at the start and end of each program
    Start Introduction to the first program Daniels and Clayton
    1:16 "Great Getting' Up Morning" Daniels and Clayton
    2:24 "Pilgrim Stanger" [also known as "I am a Pilgrim"] Daniels
    4:48 "Jenny Jenkins" Daniels and Clayton
    6:15 The story of Old Blue Clayton
    8:25 "Old Blue" [the song] Clayton
    10:37 "Whiskey is the Life of Man" Daniels and Clayton
    12:25 End of the first program Daniels and Clayton
    13:25 Introduction to the second program Daniels and Clayton
    14:10 "Drill Ye Tarriers" Daniels and Clayton
    16:14 "Go Away From My Window" Clayton
    18:58 "I Gave My Love A Cherry" Daniels and Clayton
    21:00 "Villikins and Dinah" Daniels
    23:13 "Sourwood Mountain" [A note in the collection folder calls this song "Chickens Crowin' on Sourwood NH."] Daniels and Clayton
    25:18 Conclusion of the second program Daniels and Clayton
    26:37 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR021, Recorded: 1958, RXG 0712; 26:10
    Start Introduction to the first program. Clayton says that the program will be Cowboy songs. Daniels and Clayton
    1:17 "I Ride Old Paint" Daniels and Clayton
    3:29 "Tying a Knot in the Devil's Tail" Clayton
    5:25 "The Colorado Trail" Daniels
    6:36 "Cowboy's Lament" [also known as "The Streets of Laredo"] Clayton
    9:16 ["Tender Fool"] Clayton [the first line song is: "One day I thought I'd have some fun, see how punchin' cows was done"]
    10:50 "The Old Chisholm Trail" Daniels and Clayton
    12:15 Conclusion of the first program Daniels and Clayton
    13:10 Introduction to the second program Daniels and Clayton
    14:09 "That Great Getting' Up Mornin'" Daniels and Clayton
    15:47 "Pilgrim Stanger" [also known as "I am a Pilgrim"] Daniels
    17:47 "Jenny Jenkins" Daniels and Clayton
    19:13 The story of Old Blue Clayton
    21:23 "Old Blue" [the song] Clayton
    23:33 "Whiskey Johnnie" [also known as "Whiskey is the Life of Man"] Daniels and Clayton
    25:13 Conclusion of the second program Daniels and Clayton
    26:10 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR022, Recorded: unknown, RXG 0713; 19:52
    This seems to be a recording session with Paul Clayton and Char (Charlotte) Daniels. There are false starts, laughing and some complete songs.
    Start: [recording error]
    0:35 "Abilene" Daniels
    2:09 "Old Cotton Fields at [sic] Home" Daniels
    3:35 "Abilene" Daniels
    5:29 "Make Me a Pallet on Your Floor" Daniels
    6:56 "Hush Little Baby, Don't You Cry" Daniels
    10:05 "When I First Came to This Land" Clayton and Daniels
    12:52 "Jenny Jenkins" Clayton and Daniels
    15:40 "Pay Me My Money Down" Clayton and Daniels
    17:15 "Old Cotton Fields at [sic] Home" Daniels
    19:52 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR023, Recorded: summer 1957, RXG 0714; 28:44
    This is a sample, compilation of field recordings made by Bates Littlehales in Tennessee and Alabama. He introduces the songs and the performers.
    Start "Wildwood Flower" Gerry Nelson
    1:22 "John Henry" Gerry Nelson
    2:28 "Willow Garden" Gerry Nelson
    3:35 Littlehales talks about the three previous songs, where he collected them and the performer, Gerry Nelson.
    4:38 "Old Rattler" Gerry Nelson [The melody seems to be the same as "Lay the Pistol Down, Babe, Lay the Pistol Down"]
    6:19 "Jesse James" Bobby Barker
    7:19 Littlehales introduces Kenneth Bolton
    7:28 Kenneth Bolton explains why he sing hymns.
    8:08 "Poor Wayfaring Stranger" Kenneth Bolton
    10:23 [probably "The Blind Child's Prayer"] Polly Bolton [the first line is "They say dear father that tonight"]
    12:10 "Dying Hobo" Frank Bolton [first line is "It was at a western water tank, on a cold December day"]
    14:11 "Old Joe Clark" [Lum] Thomas
    15:15 Flop Eared Mule' [Lum] Thomas
    16:34 "Sally Goodin" [Lum] Thomas
    17:39 "The Arkansas Traveler" [Lum] Thomas
    19:14 Littlehales introduces the next performer.
    19:33 "Little Mary" [also known as "The Ballad of Little Mary Phagen"] Ruby [Haveren]
    21:14 "The Swapping Song" Ruby [Haveren]
    23:30 "30 Pieces of Silver" Kenneth Bolton and friends
    25:32 "In the Pines" [Karl] Samples
    26:47 "16 Tons" Gerry Nelson
    28:44 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR024, Recorded: unknown, RXG 0715; 9:40
    There is no documentation for this tape. There is no introduction on the tape itself. It may be another recording session with Paul Clayton and Char (Charlotte) Daniels.
    Start "Tying a Knot in the Devil's Tail" Daniels
    2:15 "Stackolee" Clayton
    4:30 "Young Rogers the Miller" [takes 1 and 2] Clayton and Daniels
    5:38 "Young Rogers the Miller" [take 3] Clayton and Daniels
    7:26 "The Quaker's Daughter" [take 1] Clayton and Daniels
    9:12 "The Quaker's Daughter" [take 2] Clayton and Daniels
    9:40 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR025, Recorded: unknown, RXG 0716; 17:03
    Start "The Creation Song" Clayton and Daniels [first line is "First he made the sun"]
    1:16 "Get Down, Get Down Little Henry Lee" Clayton and Daniels
    4:15 "Ain't Got No Place to Lay My Head" Clayton and Daniels
    6:05 "Young Rogers the Miller" Clayton and Daniels
    7:48 "The Quaker Lover" Clayton and Daniels
    9:25 "Seven Drunken Nights" Clayton and Daniels [first line is "First night that I came home drunk as I could be"
    12:14 "Old Blue" Daniels
    14:20 The Frozen Logger" Clayton and Daniels
    17:03 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR026 (1), Recorded: 1960-01-08, RXG 0717; 22:14
    This is a recording for the first part of John Dildine's radio program of January 8, His guests are Sonny Terry and Brownie McGhee. All the music is from their recordings. This broadcast is concluded on SR026 (2).
    Start: "Midnight Special"
    2:45 Dildine speaks with Terry and McGhee about the blues and how they got started in the music business.
    9:05 "Fox Hunt"
    11:37 Dildine asks them about a State Department Exchange Tour they recently did in India. They talk about the harmonica work on "Fox Hunt." They talk about their music.
    17:07 "Take this hammer"
    20:05 Dildine, Terry and McGhee talk about work songs.
    22:14 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR026 (2), Recorded: 1960-01-08, RXG 0717; 22:14
    This is a recording for the second part of John Dildine's radio program of January 8, 1960. His guests are Sonny Terry and Brownie McGee. All the music is from their recordings.This broadcast is begun on SR026 (1).
    Start: Dildine, Terry and McGhee talk about the recording industry. They talk about the song "John Henry."
    3:20 "John Henry"
    7:22 Dildine, Terry, and McGhee talk about the song "John Henry." They talk about guitar tunings. They talk about the song "Betty and Dupree."
    12:39 "Betty and Dupree"
    18:53 Dildine, Terry, and McGhee talk about how Terry learned to play the harmonica. They talk about the next song.
    20:25 "Lose Your Money"
  - AFC 1975/001: SR027, Recorded: 1960-05-01, RXG 0718; 31:57
    It seems that John Dildine reused a tape to record his radio program of May 1, 1960. However, the tape was not completely erased before starting the recording, so the first (almost) nine minutes are not folk music at all.
    Start Prior to a congressional [Senate] hearing, an unidentified person from the Westinghouse Broadcasting Company attempts to do live interviews with Bobby Kennedy, Dave Beck, Nathan Shefferman and Barry Goldwater.
    5:00 The committee hearing is called to order and Mr. Schefferman testifies about 16 checks.
    8:00 An advertisement for the "Program Guide" for radio station WASH-FM in Washington, D.C.
    8:57 Start of the Dildine radio broadcast of May 1, 1960. The theme music is Etta Baker's recording of "Railroad Bill."
    10:14 Dildine introduces the program.
    11:35 Dildine talks about the theme song. He introduces Charlotte [Char] Daniels. They talk.
    14:10 "Durango Jail" Daniels
    17:00 Dildine and Daniels talk.
    19:23 "Come All Ye Fair and Tender Ladies" Daniels
    23:42 Dildine and Daniels talk.
    25:25 "Across the Blue Mountains" Daniels The first line is: "One morning, one morning, one morning in May"
    27:55 Dildine and Daniels talk about folk music and the "folk process."
    31:57 End [This broadcast is continued on SR028]
  - AFC 1975/001: SR028, Recorded: 1960-05-01, RXG 0719; 27:40
    This is the continuation of SR027, John Dildine's radio broadcast of May 1, 1960 with guest Charlotte Char Daniels.
    Start Dildine and Daniels talk about "bad man ballads."
    1:33 "Duncan and Brady" Daniels
    3:55 Dildine and Daniels talk about acoustic guitars and electric guitars. Daniels introduces the next song.
    7:20 "Blues Chase Up a Rabbit" Daniels
    10:45 Dildine and Daniels talk about the Archive of Folk Song at the Library of Congress. Dildine talks about the upcoming Washington Folk Festival and National Folk Festival.
    15:45 "I've Got a Home in That Rock" Daniels
    19:43 Dildine and Daniels talk about spirituals. The talk about "hoots."
    22:30 "Frankie and Johnnie" Daniels
    26:09 Dildine closes the radio program.
    27:40 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR029, Recorded: 1960-05-22, RXG 0719; 58:54
    The only documentation for this recording was two notes on the tape box itself: "Indian Program" and "May 22, 1960." This recording seems to be part of a radio broadcast for the World Affairs Seminar. John Dildine and another unidentified broadcast host apparently combined their air-time to have a program of Asian music. This recording is the Indian portion of that broadcast.
    Start An unidentified man introduces a program of music from India. He introduces Mr. [Ravin Tanden], the Second Secretary from the Embassy of India, "who will tell us about Indian music and will explain it to us."
    1:05 A recorded, instrumental piece of music is played. [flute, drums, and drone]
    4:30 Dildine calls the previous piece "a morning raga." Mr. [Tanden] says that it is a classical piece. He explains it. Dildine and [Tanden] discuss the raga musical form and other aspects of Indian music. Unidentified man joins the conversation. They introduce and explain the next piece, which is also a morning raga. A stringed instrument, a sarod, is the lead instrument on this recorded piece.
    14:30 The second morning raga is played. Mr. [Tanden] occasionally talks over the music to explain something.
    38:10 Unidentified man discusses the World Affairs Seminar and how this program fits in. There is discussion of the raga which was just played: the audience for this music; how an Indian musician learns his/her profession; the history of Indian music. They discuss "the social context" of Indian music. They discuss how western music is coming into India. The next piece is introduced.
    51:02 This is a recording of a vocal selection, with instrumental backup, from South India.
    54:24 The next selection is introduced. It features a woodwind instrument.
    55:00 A recording is played.
    58:20 Unidentified man concludes the Indian portion of the program.
    58:54 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR030 (1), Recorded: 1960-06-05, RXG 0720; 40:33
    This is a recording for a John Dildine radio broadcast. It was recorded at a house in Georgetown, Washington, D.C. The performers are Bob Beers, Evelyn Beers, Judy Weston and Dave Sear. They are in D.C. for the National Folk Festival. The Beers and Sear performed at the festival. The recording volume is uneven. The first 24+ minutes of this broadcast are repeated on SR031.
    Start Dildine introduces the performance and the performers. In the background a woman [Judy Weston] is singing and playing banjo. Dildine and Bob Beers discuss the psaltry and the hammered dulcimer. They discuss the first song, which Bob Beers wrote and will perform on his dulcimer.
    4:36 "The Rain Forest" Bob Beers
    8:40 Dildine does a station break. He introduces Judy Weston. They talk about learning songs from phonograph records.
    15:55 "Willie Moore" Judy Weston
    14:10 Dildine asks Weston from which recording she learned the song. They discuss the sources of her songs. Sear joins the conversation. Sear discusses the next song.
    18:18 "John Henry" Dave Sear
    23:05 Dildine and Sear discuss how Sear put together his arrangement. Dildine does a station break. Dildine talks with Evelyn Beers.
    29:05 "The Water is Wide" Evelyn [vocal] and Bob Beers
    31:30 "Bonnie George Campbell" Evelyn [vocal] and Bob Beers
    33:38 Dildine and Bob Beers talk about fiddling.
    35:18 "So Early, Early in the Spring" Judy Weston
    38:50 "Aiken Drum" or "Achen Drum" Dave Sear [and others on the chorus]
  - AFC 1975/001: SR030 (2), Recorded: 1960-06-05, RXG 0721; 2:25
    These few segments may have been recorded at the same time as SR031. There is no documentation available.
    Start [unidentified song] Judy Weston
    1:21 [tuning instruments]
    1:50 [unidentified song] Bob Beers
    2:25 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR031, Recorded: 1960-06-05, RXG 0722; 24:14
    This is a recording for a John Dildine radio broadcast. It was recorded at a house in Georgetown, Washington, D.C. The performers are Bob Beers, Evelyn Beers, Judy Weston and Dave Sear. They are in D.C. for the National Folk Festival. The Beers and Sear performed at the festival. The recording volume good. A portion of this broadcast is on SR030.
    Start Dildine introduces the performance and the performers. Dildine and Bob Beers discuss the psaltery and the hammered dulcimer. They discuss the first song, which Bob Beers wrote and will perform on his dulcimer.
    4:15 "The Rain Forest" Bob Beers
    8:07 Dildine does a station break. He introduces Judy Weston. They talk about learning songs from phonograph records.
    12:10 "Willie Moore" Judy Weston
    13:50 Dildine asks Weston from which recording she learned the song. They discuss the sources of her songs. Sear joins the conversation. Sear discusses the next song.
    17:18 "John Henry" Dave Sear
    21:25 Dildine and Sear discuss how Sear put together his arrangement.
    23:40 Dildine does a station break.
    24:14 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR032, Recorded: 1960-06-10, RXG 0723; 22:10
    This is the first portion of John Dildine's radio broadcast. His guest is Dave Sear (and his banjo). The broadcast is continued on SR033. The song list for this collection indicates that Virginia (Ginny) Dildine accompanies Sear on all the songs. I found no documentation of this on the actual tape boxes and my ear did not hear it.
    Start "Railroad Bill" [recorded] leads into a John Dildine radio broadcast. His guest is Dave Sear.
    2:20 "Old Dan Tucker" Sear
    3:43 Dildine and Sear discuss how Sear came to be a singer of folk sings.
    6:25 "Go Tell Aunt Rhodie" Sear
    8:40 Dildine and Sear discuss playing and singing fold songs.
    10:45 Dildine does a station break.
    12:20 Dildine and Sear discuss simplicity and art.
    12:42 "Freight Train Blues" Sear
    15:26 Dildine and Sear discuss the "Freight Train Blues." The talk about who writes the songs and the music. Dildine asks "what kind of music [Sear] likes to play best." They discuss British ballads. They discuss folk music as a form of communication.
    21:50 Sear begins to introduce the next song.
    22:10 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR033, Recorded: 1960-06-10, RXG 0724; 31:31
    This is the second portion of John Dildine's radio broadcast. His guest is Dave Sear (and his banjo). The broadcast is begun on SR032. The song list for this collection indicates that Virginia (Ginny) Dildine accompanies Sear on all the songs. I found no documentation of this on the actual tape boxes and my ear did not hear it.
    Start Dildine and Sear talk about folk music as a form of communication.
    0:50 "East Virginia Blues" Sear
    4:20 Dildine does a station break.
    5:08 Dildine is given a note, which he reads, giving the attribution of "Freight Train Blues."
    6:00 Sear discusses what songs he chooses to play for what audience.
    7:30 "Hiram Hubbard" Sear
    10:35 Dildine and Sear discuss how a performer selects his/her songs. Dildine says that he's had another phone call. This one is about a folk singer Named Dave Shear. Sear introduces his next song.
    13:34 "Cotton Fields" Sear
    16:21 Dildine and Sear talk about Lead Belly songs. They discuss "honesty" in folk music.
    18:08 Dildine does a station break.
    19:13 Dildine asks Sear to sing a "commercial" song. They discuss "what a folk song is and what a folk singer is."
    22:30 "Mighty Joe Magarac" Sear
    25:00 Dildine and Sear discuss the previous song and get ready for the next song.
    27:05 "Swing Low Sweet Chariot" Sear
    29:15 Dildine closes the broadcast. Repeat of "Railroad Bill"
    31:31 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR034, Recorded: 1960-07-17, RXG 0725; 29:45
    This is a broadcast of John Dildine's radio show. Donal Leace is his guest. Leace is from West Virginia and is currently a student at Howard University.
    Start Dildine introduces the broadcast and Donal Leace. Leace introduces the first song.
    1:21 "Hound Dog Bay at the Moon" Leace
    4:06 Dildine and Leace discuss the previous song. They discuss work songs and suffering. They discuss using songs to bring history alive. Dildine asks Leace to sing a children's song. Leace introduces the next song.
    8:00 "All the Pretty Little Horses" Leace
    9:58 Leace and Dildine discuss the previous song. They discuss sad songs and happy songs. They discuss folk music, classical music and jazz.
    14:25 Dildine does a station break.
    15:42 Dildine and Leace discuss the Cauldron, a folk music venue on Wednesday nights. Dildine differentiates between D.C. hootenannies and N.Y. hootenannies. Leace says that Philadelphia has no folk music radio shows. Leace introduces the next song.
    20:25 "John Hardy" Leace
    22:42 Dildine and Leace talk about "John Hardy" and "John Henry." They discuss the universality of legends and folk songs. Leace introduces the next song.
    25:47 "I Want Jesus to Walk with Me" Leace
    26:45 Dildine closes the broadcast. ["Railroad Bill" is playing in the background.]
    28:45 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR035, Recorded: 1960-12-25, RXG 0726; 24:31
    This is the first part of a recording John Dildine made with Jean and George Foss to be broadcast at a later date. The second part of this recording is on SR036.
    Start Dildine introduces Jean and George Foss. George says that they are mostly interested in old Scottish and English ballads. Jean says that they both attended Julliard, graduating in 1954 and 1955. George and Jean talk about their non-folk-singing work.
    2:25 [The original tape box calls this song "House Carpenter." Google search suggests other possible titles: "The Daemon Lover" and "The Lover's Ghost."] Jean Foss, vocal; George Foss, 4-string dulcimer The first line of this song is: "Well met, well met my own true love."
    5:47 Jean and George talk about where and from whom the collected this song. They mention collecting with Paul Clayton. George talks about the lap dulcimer he played on the previous song. They discuss the next song.
    9:38 "Lady Gay" George Foss vocal [and dulcimer]
    12:20 George discusses where they learned the previous song. Dildine takes a station break. [There is dead air for about 40 seconds.] Dildine discusses what is to follow.
    14:50 "Fair and Tender Ladies" Jean Foss, vocal
    18:40 Dildine, Jean and George discuss the previous song. They discuss the next song.
    21:10 "Across the Blue Mountains" George Foss The first line is: "One morning, one morning, one morning in May"
    23:23 George discusses the previous song and the woman from whom he learned it. Dildine does a station break.
    24:31 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR036, Recorded: 1960-12-25, RXG 0727; 24:41
    This is the second part of a recording John Dildine made with Jean and George Foss to be broadcast at a later date. The first part of this recording is on SR035.
    Start Dildine says that after the next song Jean and George Foss will sing Christmas songs. Jean says that the next song is a children's song and a song of contradictions.
    1:02 "Nottamun Town" Jean Foss
    3:45 Dildine, Jean and George discuss a Coventry carol. The tune is from Kentucky, the sharp collection.
    4:50 [The title is probably "The Cherry Tree Carol"] George Foss, unaccompanied The first line is: "When Joseph Was an Olden Man"
    8:35 Dildine and George discuss the previous song. Dildine and Jean discuss the next song. She explains the Coventry plays.
    10:50 "Lilylulay" Jean Foss The first line is "Lay the Tiny Little Child." Google search yields the title "Coventry Carol – Version 1."
    12:50 Dildine takes a station break. [dead air time of about 01:10] George introduces the next two songs.
    15:57 "Mary Had a Baby" Jean and George Foss vocal, banjo accompaniment
    16:05 The tape box records the title as "Glory, Virgin Mary." Google search yields other possible titles: "Pretty Little Baby (Virgin Mary)" and "What you gonna call your pretty little baby" Jean and George Foss The first line is: "Hey Mary what you gonna call your pretty little baby"
    17:12 Jean and George discuss the next song and from whom they collected it.
    17:45 "Mary" Jean Foss
    20:10 Dildine says there may be time for one last song.
    20:25 "I Wonder and I Wander" George Foss vocal and lap dulcimer
    23:05 Dildine closes the program.
    24:41 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR037 (1), Recorded: late summer 1960, RXG 0728; 31:21
    This is a recording for a John Dildine radio program with Carolyn Hester and Richard (Dick) Fariña.
    Start Dildine introduces Carolyn Hester and Richard (Dick) Fariña. They were married 11 weeks prior to the date of this recording. Hester talks about why she has kept her maiden name.
    2:03 "Santiano" Fariña and Hester
    5:18 Fariña and Hester discuss a verse in the previous song which they changed.
    6:40 "Bridget and Hogan" Fariña and Hester, a cappella
    8:43 Dildine and Fariña discuss the previous song and folk singing in Ireland.
    10:15 Dildine takes a station break. Hester and Fariña decide which song to sing next.
    11:25 "Mary Had a Baby" Hester and Fariña
    13:36 Hester says she learned the previous song from Howard Mitchell and then found it in Ruth Crawford Seeger's book "Songs for Children." They discuss possible origins of the song. Dildine asks Hester how she selects traditional songs versus commercial songs. Fariña adds to the discussion. Hester and Fariña discuss the next song.
    20:50 "Rum by Gum" Hester and Fariña
    22:48 Dildine, Hester and Fariña discuss the previous song and what may be its source. Dildine takes a station break. Dildine plays a song by Odetta from her album "Odetta at the Gate of Horn." Dildine
    29:15 Dildine, Hester and Fariña discuss the Gate of Horn night club in Chicago. They discuss Hester's upcoming performance schedule.
    31:21 End
  - AFC 1975/001: SR037 (2), Recorded: unknown, RXG 0728; 30:16
    This is a recording of "Pan American Melodies from the House of the Americas." This probably is a tape that Dildine used only on the reverse side and did not use or erase this side.
    Start noise then blank
    0:30 The announcer [Bill Cerri] opens a broadcast of Pan American Melodies from the House of the Americas, the Pan American Union.
    1:32 Musical performance from Argentina
    3:50 The announcer identifies the prior performance and introduces the next performance.
    4:00 Musical performance from Mexico
    12:39 The announcer discusses the Organization of the American States (OAS).
    14:23 Musical performance from Venezuela